hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream
88.1 on September 17th
2024 we're here with hunar Abdul Raman
and we'll be discussing what is the
limit of our brains there's a fun
backstory here maybe we'll go into there
will be a presentation
followed by a discussion so I'm very
much looking forward to it and to
reading people's comments and questions
too so honard thank you again for
joining and to you for any backstory and
introduction and for the presentation so
thanks
again H thank you Daniel for inviting me
to this nice stream actually it's the
first time uh as I told you before we
start to do a live stream uh using this
software so I hope the audience will
forgive us if there is any upcoming
technical problem problems hopefully
there will be not uh so thanks a lot for
inviting me again my name is hun I have
a PhD in
Neuroscience uh I spent many many years
trying to learn how our brain works
using functional MRI EEG so I did my PhD
at from I I get my PhD from the
Cambridge University uh and uh and we we
will be talking a bit about what I did
in my PhD and how I try to link my the
concepts that I learn about brain with
with the outside
world with with with other Concepts like
the free energy so I'm actually a
newcomer to the free energy principle I
hope that people with technical
background forgive us if I have any
technical errors but hopefully maybe we
will I I'll try to learn and share my
insights about what I have discovered
from my
searching in the past few years so uh is
it can you see the slides if I start
great so uh the topic is actually about
what's the limit of our brain and I will
try to uh talk about two two concepts I
I I'll talky about some few Concepts and
later on we will link them all together
so first I'll try to talk about the
brain as a predictive machine usually
the predictive coding account then I
will try to use into the free energy
principles and uh and then later on I
will try to talk about what makes
prediction difficult I will talk about
extrinsic factors so even if I have if
we have the best learning machine the
best machine learning algorithm or even
if our brain is perfect in learning
there are still a lot of uh difficulties
uh basically because of computational
irreducibility principle which I will be
talking more about it in the upcoming
slides so I will try to I would love to
start with repetition suppression is a
well-known Concept in Neuroscience so uh
if if somebody wants to go into the
details with repetition suppression I
will recommend to you uh this article by
my PhD supervisor R Hansen uh but it's a
bit difficult to wrap your hand around
the results so I I'll try to make it
easy basically what repetition
suppression means uh the activity that
we record from our brains whether using
EEG fmri or uh single cell recordings is
the for for example if you see a
sequence of pictures of elephants and
then later on you will see something
surprising or novel like the kangaro
image here the activity of our brain
increases
increases however when we when you see
repetitions of the same image again like
the Kang here the activity decreases
that's what we call a repetition
separation if you repeat something the
activity of your brain your your brain
will not be responding in the same way
it responded the first
time then you will see something new
like this beer here uh because it's
novel The activity of of your brain
increases again so so this repetition
suppression is not only for repetition
it sometimes we call it expectation
suppression so so even if something is
not repeated but not expected the
activity of your brain increases but if
you expect something so during it's
usually repetition and expectation are
synonymous if something repeats a lot it
will be expected if something is novel
it's unexpected so these results you
will be finding in whether repetition
studies or uh expectation studies they
will tell you if you see something
unexpected or novel The recordings of
your brain increases if something become
expected or repeated the recordings
decrease so that's the repetition
suppression now uh during my PhD we we
uh saw a a very interesting paper titled
Les is more expectations sharpens
representations in the primary cortex so
so normally a neuroscientist will be
interesting why this happens why
repetition sepration is there so this
paper
uh proposed a new idea which actually uh
a bit surprising for us so the paper
tested these are grating
orientations uh the subject will see
different orientations sometimes it's
expected sometimes it's not expected so
the results they found is that the
activity of the brain decreases when
something is expected
or so this was expectation study not
repetition study but same usually the
results will be similar so the activity
decreases as you see here uh I I you
don't see my mouse can you see my my
curser oh
okay so the activity decreases however
for
classification
uh they they tested classification
accuracy so so they have like two
orientations they so if you repeat
something if you use machine learning to
classify between
orientations in the repetition the class
ification accuracy is
more so let me
see uh okay so during uh this is the
classification the the the bottom panel
is about the classification accuracy so
as you see in the repetition the
classification accuracy increases and
they their explanation was that because
sharpening happens so I will give you an
uh uh an illustration so this is not the
exact experiment but this uh
registration so for example here you see
the number five if you repeat that
basically it will become sharper I mean
the the neurons that's the concept that
are not directly representing number
five will be suppressed so when you
repeat something or when something
become expected the non-interested
activity will become suppressed so
that's their explanation basically it's
sharpening something the image will
become sharper uh I think this
this is intuitive
explanation uh
however we uh so during my PhD we did
have a lot of data set about repetition
so two different data sets we have one
data set
was pictures of faces versus scrumbled
faces were shown to the subjects so you
see here two faces similar repeated and
then you see here two scrum faces
repeated we also have the data for
grings
orientations it's similar we do have
either repetitions or novel uh so what
we found in our uh results is saying the
repetition the activity decreases we saw
but uh for the phase data set we saw
that even the classification accuracy
also decreases so it means like when you
repeat something uh the brain activity
decreases but for the greatting we all
we saw that the classification increases
so the same result as the previous Group
which I talked about they found they
they they explain that as sharpening so
how can we explain this results because
for the grating data set we see the
classification accuracy increases so we
can say oh it's sharpening but now for
the faces the classification accuracy
decreases so what is that uh so we
thought like it will be very very
difficult without simulations just uh
just uh explain the data with our minds
intuition doesn't work to be quite
honest without simulation so the reason
because functional MRI is uh even though
it's high resolution it's still very
very low each pix each boxel here
represents the activity of millions of
neurons AAG together so so basically
when we are try saying that uh
sharpening it means that non interested
neurons will become less active we are
talking about the aage activity of many
many many neurons and it will be very
very difficult to intuition about that
without simulation so so this
representation will tell you like for
example uh here we we are talking about
uh different uh uh representations of
the data it will be very very difficult
to uh to to conceptualize what happens
really in the underlying uh the
underlying
mechanism uh so what we proposed was we
thought like maybe classification
accuracy also decreases for local
scaling or local uh so so what people
think uh you see here in the uh first
panel so I just I'm just wondering where
can can you see the mouse when I am
moving
it yeah it's small but we can see it
I'll I'll also go with my mouse too
because I have two screens to be quite
honest I I mean which screen you see the
mouse moving so that
yeah we see the mouse we see the mouse
on P1
uniform oh okay okay so so this screen
okay I I just okay great so so five here
H if you repeat the five people usually
think that Separation Will happens
uniformly so you can see the five
suppressed with all the videos so
sharpening will tell you no that the
suppression will not happen re uniformly
it only happens with the non interested
neurons or neurons that doesn't
represent five but we say that even if
neurons for example the neurons that
represent five even we if we selectively
suppress those neurons like in the
bottom panel we may still find increase
in classification accuracy depending on
how many voxels or we we suppressed so
basically this was our conceptual idea
before
simulations so how do we simulate data I
mean how do we go from the neural
activity to the fun MRI because the
simulation is kind of difficult because
we are trying to express neural activity
in the functional MRI so one idea is for
example this is from neural activity
studies from a single neuron uh let's
say this neuron is very active uh for
orientation if if the orientation is 90
degree so you see a lot of spikes here
and and the if you if you represent that
with a tuning curve you will see that it
will have maximum response when the
orientation is at
19 but but the response of the neuron
will be less if you go because we will
say this neuron is very selective to the
orientation
19 so the way we simulated that we we
simulated that using orientation curves
so let's say this orientation curve is
uh is selected to the horizontal uh uh
orientation uh but it's less selective
to to the
orientations what sharpening means it
means it becomes sharper when when you
repeat that the neuron will be more
selective to the horizontal selum so
this is less sharpening this is more
sharpening so that's how we try we are
trying to simulate that now on the other
hand scaling or dampening it means like
the the activity will be decreased the
activity of the neuron will be increased
for for
the horizontal stimulate
now we we have a lot of neurons not one
neuron so this was only a representation
for one neuron but we have a lot of
neurons some neurons are responding to
the orientation 19 some neurons are
responding to or to the horizontal
orientation and some in between and
there is overlapping and when we want to
simulate a voxel we usually sum this
line the activities on the
sline uh so I I I don't know if it's is
clear or not the the the procedure that
we are trying to do so uh hope you
interrupt me if something is unclear so
when we sum the
activities we will have a representation
for the activity of a voxel now uh in
this case we talked about sharpening and
uh scaling but we have we may have a
Global Effect and a Global Effect means
everything will be suppressed everything
so so this is the global effect the
local effect it means know selectively a
part of uh neurons will be suppressed so
this is similar to the
sharpening uh we call it remote effect
it means that the neuron that responds
to the horizontal uh stimuli it won't be
suppressed but the neurons that respond
to other orientations they will be sup
according to their distance so this is a
parameter that we can find to and local
suppression it means the opposite the
neuron that is selected to the
horizontal stimul it will be suppressed
so you see there are many ways that we
can
stimulate the the repetition
suppression so we identified six ways to
to represent repetition suppression
either we have Global so the red one
represents the after repetition what
happens to the neural tuni curves after
repetition so either the global
everything is suppressed or everything
is sharpened become narrower or we we
have local the the stimulus of Interest
the effect will be more concentrated on
the stimulus of Interest or we have
remote the effect will be more
concentrated on the neurons that are far
away from the stimulus of
Interest so for the completion we
actually examined six other models we
call them shifting models but they are
not important because we don't think our
brain will behave like that but but just
for completeness so so for those who
want to do a mathematical modeling it's
just like for here G is the tuning curve
which is represented by X and mu which
is the mean of the tunic curve and sigma
which is how how much narrow is the
tunic curve and then we multiply it by a
factor which is C that's the suppressing
Factor so so in local scaling we
suppress the tuni C in in in sharpening
models we suppress the uh the sigma or
the how much narrow is and then in
shifting models we we shift the tunic C
so for more technical details you can
actually go to the to our paper and see
more details about how did we simulate
that uh uh and as I said we have two
data sets the phase data set and the
grating data set so what we want we want
to see if our Sim if we can use our
simulations to to match uh our
findings uh and actually using
functional MRI we actually identified
some other features we didn't only use
uh repetition separation and uh
classification we identified uh six more
uh data features and we want to see if
we can actually use the simulations to
uh explain that and the results which we
found was very very interesting so this
green uh circles it means that that
specific model so remember we we We
examined 12 models in total 12 different
models so if it is green it means this
model can explain this functional MRI
feature if it's red it means it can't
explain so for Global scaling you can
see it can explain a lot of features but
except BC which uh I didn't have time
to these are functional MRI features you
can see this is the data and we are
trying to fit it uh
so the interesting thing is you only see
local model local scaling can actually
explain all the features so you don't
see any red circles here for both data
sets so it can qualitatively explain all
the features that we saw in our data all
the other models they they can
individually they can explain individual
features for example here sharpening
model can can uh explain uh repetition
separation can explain within
correlations can explain between
correlation but it can't explain for
example the features of sharpening in
our phase data set so the short story
long is as as the long story short story
we find that local scaling best
represent our uh the findings of our
data so the the basically the local
scaling it means that the Bas model is
the model that predict when we repeat
the neuron that uh that are selective to
that feature it will be suppressed the
most not Global and not sharpening the
the suppression of the neuron that so
basically what that means if you
see a horizontal orientation the neurons
that are specific to this uh horizontal
orientation they will be suppressed more
the more selectivity to that they will
be more suppressed the there are reasons
we like the results like that so
basically later on the paper which we
actually uh introduced later they did
similar
uh simulation to us and they actually
found similar conclusions that uh these
model this neuron is uh this model is
based explains the our data
set so the the reason we like uh local
failing or dampening uh
it it's become it's because very
parsimonious it can be explained easily
without like instigating complicated
explanation so basically it just means
that AAP synaptic fatigue so when you
when you stimulate a neuron when a
neuron is stimulated it it will get
tired and then it will be more
suppressed when you repeat something so
this is a parous explanation and the
second reason why we like this result
because now trying to connect it with
predictive coding literature and with
the free energy principle but first with
the predictive coding
literature we think this result is more
in line with web because you see in in
predictive coding literature you usually
see this image Al lot you will say oh
you have a a stimuli and then you have a
prediction the lower upper even of your
brain try to predict and there will be
an error and you have a prediction error
so the question is that what this
prediction error represents we think
that these results will tell us that the
prediction error is the Unexplained data
so
it's nowhere says that the prediction
error is the noise it's usually the non
explained stimuli so the part that you
can't explain and that we think is
actually more in line with with the
suppression with the with this
model I will actually come back to this
uh later uh but
but uh first I want to talk about so so
we established that our brain is a
prediction machine and and the results
in our functional MRI actually supports
that our brain seemingly it it's not
interested in expected stimulate because
it has predicted that our brain trying
to predict the nonexpected that's why
more activity is being exploited for
novel or non explained uh stimuli so
what's the enemy of prediction so if our
brain is a prediction machine
what makes uh what's what are the
obstacles in front of our the ability or
our brain to predict
things so I'll will tell you a story
that I faced I I'm usually interested
train MRI at some point of my of my life
I was trying to train a neuron Network
to predict mandal bradet and the reason
why I thought mandal bradet is more
interesting than language predictions
predicting the next token because from
Mandel Mandel br you actually know the
ground truth the ground truth is
actually if you copy this JavaScript
line into a JavaScript it will produce a
mandal bro it's very very easy it's few
lines of Goode just one equation it will
produce and then when you change these
numbers you can zoom in to this mandal
bradet so for mandal bradet I know
actually what's the ground truth it's
not like the language I for language I
don't know what's the best ground to it
is is my sentence is the best is my is
your sentence which phrasing is the
ground truth we so so that it's very
difficult to identify the ground truth
in language models but for Mandel bro we
know what's the ground truth and that's
why I was interested to train neural
networks to predict Mandel bro
said uh so the surprising thing for me I
thought this will be easy because Mandel
bro has a lot of regularities a lot of
uh places where it repeats so I thought
this will be easy task but I was shocked
I mean even when I used a neural network
uh with very very big size to predict
different parts of so you can train a
neural network to do to predict a
specific part that's easy but when you
want to generalize it will be very
difficult the reason is because I was
underestimating melro there are it's
true that there are a lot of
regularities but the more you zoom in
there are there will be always new
features it's mindblowing how this
simple line of precursor they will
always present you with something new
that your model or the newal network no
matter how bit how how good is trained
it can't predict any anything
so so so that the puzzle for me actually
we know that record neuron Network are
twoing complete so it is possible that
you can train a neural network to
simulate the code but in that case the
neuron network will not help you in
prediction it will just simulate the
same code for you the the the main hope
that we have with neural network is that
we predict ahead of time we predict two
steps ahead of time or three steps ahead
of time not not just
recursively uh predict One Step
because that's what uh which I will came
later on on computational iru of that uh
so so before coming to computational
irreducibility so this is my first time
when I saw there is a challenge in
prediction it's it's it's it's very
difficult uh to predict these intricate
features NeverEnding emergent
patterns so one one of the reasons this
is phrased by Steven walram is the
principle of computational equivalence
so basically if you manage to train a
recurrent neural network to simulate the
same
that that predict that that actually
generate mental BR it means that in the
underlying Le at the underlying level
the they are doing the same thing they
are doing the same
computation so you basically according
to this principle you cannot simulate a
rule with another rule that are more
efficient that basically if you if you
simulate them at their most basic level
so you can simulate rule a with rule B
and then rule B can actually predict two
steps ahead of rule B that's not
possible so this may be difficult to
understand but the way Stephen Wolfram
did it he explained that in his T talk
so uh he actually so basically that in
in his T talk he was like I'm
paraphrasing he was like saying okay you
have this simple rule so this is just
like a mandal br rule you you just gave
this rule to computer and then it will
prod use for you a pattern these are
stepbystep patterns and then it will
tell you if if you could is it is it
possible to predict ahead of time just
from knowing the rule I mean you know
the rule just just like we know the
Theory of Everything can we uh can we
actually predict ahead of time without
simulating the intermediate steps and I
actually don't know if it's true or not
but I believe that because Steven Wan
have spent like his Decades of his life
trying to do this and he says that this
is not
possible you have to you have to compute
all the steps you have to compute all
the steps and he even put a price for
that uh the reason why I believe
computational reducibility principles
should be it must be true because it's
uh in essence it's similar to two other
uh principles godel's incompleteness
theorem and the halting prod problem in
in spirit if you think more about it
they you you will see them that the
these are all talking about probably the
same phenomena but in different so what
I learned is that complexity is easy to
generate actually uh it was a very
shocking thing for me but I have been
simulating these simple rules and then
they for a while and I I they always
surprise me what they are can produce
very simple rules you find in them and
you can generate but the problem is it's
hard to understand and this is because
of um that principle which is was which
was formulated by Steven W which is the
says computational irreducibility
principes so basically let's say we have
two systems system one and system two
and then system one tries to predict
system two so if if system one can
predict system two with less
computational power then we can say that
system 2 is reducible and this system
one is analogous to our brain and system
two is analogous to the environment on
the world which we are trying to to
learn
about so what stepen w found that he
examined so many different rules uh and
and the reason why he examined actually
cellular automata because of their
simplicity so what he found that is each
rule
are producing unique patterns so uh
actually by by looking at these uh
patterns you can see what computational
equivalence means it just means that you
you can you can stimulate for example
this uh pattern using another Rule now
there are some rules that are faster
than itself that's what I mean now there
are rules that are T in complete like
the rule
0 but even if you manage to initialize
the rule number 10 to produce another
rule it will not produce it faster I
mean yeah you can't use it two steps
ahead of time so so some of these rules
will be uh trapped into repetition and
some of these rules will never be able
to predict what comes
next and I thought there is another
phenomena like that it's the irrational
numbers versus rational numbers they are
actually similar to that because we have
irrational number and their their
definition is if you go what the
definition they they will never trap
into repetition so we have Pi which is a
very simple rule it's just the
circumference divided by radius it's a
very very simple rule if you simulate
that rule it will always give you a new
pattern a new number and the same for
the square root of 2 three so this is
amazing I mean I I don't know why I
didn't thought about that before Steven
wol from talking about SAR automata
think because I thought like these are
actually have the same amazement so if
you have a generative it's just and and
actually we usually talk about
universality Turing complete
universality so they will tell you uh if
you have an infinite T and if you have a
reader a writer and speciic rules you
can compute everything and they will
call that tuning complete
universality now according to Steven
moram he actually revised the what what
does it mean by computation universality
so so he usually uh explains that in the
term of cellular automata but I will try
to explain that in in the term of
irrational and irrational numbers so
it's actually a bit mindblowing but we
we we usually don't think about it like
that so let's say Pi that's the
definition the definition means this
rule will never trap inter unlike the
rational Ru so the rational numbers if
you divide them at some point they will
repeat they will repeat they will never
give new patterns uh but but irrational
numbers so that
means if you if you compute Pi for
Infinity it is possible that at some
point you will find the same pattern
that the square represents the square Ro
of two so so if you if you compute Pi
for Infinity it's possible that you can
find a squ of one one one one one but
but it will never trap into that rtion
at some point it will it will change so
so that means in every irrational number
you have the other irrational numbers
embedded in it it there is no way to say
this is not true because if you say this
is not true it means that these patterns
will be trapped at some point into a
cyclic
repetition but if they don't trap they
will always give you noil and that means
so someone can tell you Pi is toing
complete why because he says like if you
if you if you keep Computing Pi for
Infinity at some point you will find
that compute my genetics the same
sequence that if you represent it as a
number I I I you can say this is not
true can you I mean do do you have a
comment Daniel about oh it's a it's a
great connection it just makes me think
like within Pi is every possible
operating system every possible Note
file you could write to yourself so it's
like it contains all of these things and
also it's a great connection with the
computational classes from Wolf exactly
exactly because from usually represents
rule number 30 it says that oh this rule
number 30 you can see all patterns are
there so if you go for Infinity I think
it's a computational universality is
there it's just he just can't formalize
and I think it's the same to be quite
honest I mean if you go if you say it's
it doesn't repeat it means that it even
though the rule is very simple Pi is the
simplest possible rule it's just the
circumference divided by radius it's the
simplest possible Rule and and then you
have an imaginable sequence patterns so
okay this is interesting but this is
also problematic because it tells you a
prediction with 100% accuracy is
impossible possible remember we talked
about the super intelligence we said
that oh AGI is is actually near but many
people will say oh if AGI is near then
we will have intelligence ASI artificial
super intelligence will be just in the
corner about the corner I don't think so
because of computational irreducibility
it means that AGI will also face the
same problems that the problem is you
have to compute to be this system you
have to you have to have
Universe siiz computer that simulate our
universe faster and I don't think AI can
have that because it lives in the same
environment like this so so that it it
reaches the same ceiling that we
actually reached which means that at the
age of unknowledge at the age of
uncertainty the AGI will also suffer
from uncertainity just like
us so H okay so I talked about that that
even if we know the rule of everything
so I was
when I was younger I was always
following the physics news because I was
very
very happy to see if a physicist will
find the theory of everything because I
thought oh if stepen um if if step
Hawking can find the theory of
everything that will be the happiest day
because it can we can explain but but
now I see this is not possible I mean
even if you know that even if you put
theoretically I thought like this is the
difficult part but this is not even the
difficult part even if if we say this is
easy we have all the atoms the state
their velocity their position in our
inside our computer or even if we have a
a very powerful computer that compute uh
that compute and predict the next St it
will just produce the next update which
is the next p second or whatever is the
smallest type update plank level so that
means it means to to simulate the to
predict the future you have to simulate
the future you have to simulate the
present past than the universe itself
and that's impossible unless we are
outside the universe and we have we can
somehow simulate everything faster than
our
universe so okay so how do we how do we
do that I mean in the beginning I told I
told you that our brain is a prediction
machine you know we can predict things
so how prediction is possible in this
system the only way I can think that
prediction is possible is because two
things memorization and OB abration the
reason why I didn't put memorization
before abstraction because memorization
is not very without abstraction
memorization is not useful because
memorization it means if something
repeat then if you memorize it later on
you just cat that and if something cat
that it will be computationally very
easy to predict but that will be
possible if we if we live in a
computationally reducible universe if
something repeats memorization will be
great but if we live in a
computationally irreducible when there
is always emergent pattern memorization
is doesn't help the reason because you
should have infinite size memory to pred
to to store all the all the emergent
patterns you have to have abstraction
with memorization it
means just like uh so so remember that
previously before AI people store pixels
inside the computer just using
memorization but what neural networks do
does is they memorize but not just using
that it will abstract the information
before memorization so so so you just
don't memorize the data like itself you
you have to find a way to find the
useful uh so so that's the formal
definition I actually gave that to Jack
and that's his which I like it actually
more than the Wikipedia definition uh is
the process of reducing complexity by
focusing on main ideas and knowledge
specific details so that's the only way
that we can beat the comput isal
irreducible it's just we pay attention
to what matters for our
survival so you can see I am trying to
actually reconnect back to the active
inference so there are many ways to abct
there AR many different algorithms but I
think the easiest one is uh that's what
they usually introduce you in category
Theory they just say oh we we just gave
a same name to everything because uh so
let's say we have Bob Al Jo and if you
if want to do statistics or you want to
find any any relationship we just need
to group things according to their
similarity so similarity is actually a
very complex topic it's not just easy to
say according to similarity but but be
with me right now so course graining is
actually simpler because course graining
you group things according to proximity
proximity is easier to Define that
similarity you just say if things they
have
audian distance then specific threshold
you just group them so course graining
actually used everywhere I'm I'm
surprised course graining is
not not so much well known but it's it's
it's used everywhere another thing which
may be more familiar to your group is
Mark of blankets I think Mark of blanket
is also a more sophisticated way of
abstraction uh the reason why micro for
for example here you see these notes the
parent nodes the children nodes and the
partner nodes they are and and eternal
nodes so in the mark of blanket become
stable you can just treat this as one
entity so just just like another way of
abstraction so we say anything inside
this membrane is just one entity
anything inside this house the house is
one entity with everything that happens
inside I don't care about only when
somebody comes outside the house I
should care about but when they are
inside about I I should just look at the
house so my my point is that the stable
membranes can abstract things for us
uh linear regression is another way to
abst information but linear regression
is just a more sophisticated way of
course graining because we are using a
weighted in course grain we just aage uh
the nearby information but here uh we we
are doing uh weighted regession weighted
summation uh so we have neuron Network
as well neuron network is the most
sophisticated way of obstruction so far
uh so so course graining let me just
give you a bit about Co grain the
importance of Co graining so I mean it's
self-explanatory you just aage the
nearby pixels or the nearby uh so so
what I think about talk about why course
draining is important there is a
simulation called part particle life
simulation I have a video about that a
detail B but let me just I don't know
why this particle simulation is not more
uh familiar among the scientists uh it's
it's actually a more interesting extent
of the game of life I don't know who
invented that but there are old
videos seven years ago doing this
particle simulations I didn't have the
code back then when I wanted to
restimulate that so I improvised the
code and I was shocked that the reason
why I I I just wanted to simulate a
primordial soup where you have uh where
you have some particles attracting each
other so so you can see these few lines
of code these few lines of code just
represent present particles attracting
with to each other according to Newton's
law something similar to Newton's law so
the the inner loop here is just says if
if the distance is
this you have an attraction force or a
repulsion force uh parameterized by G so
so g g parameter
actually determines the attraction of
repulsion forces so so just a less than
a page L of code and and when you have
this rule you can simulate this R for
example you can specify how green
particles attracted to each other and
how red particles attracted to so just
few lines of code and you will have so
many interesting patterns so many
interesting patterns so so we we have
made a C++ software about that it's
available on our GitHub uh so it's it's
just amazing how complexity is easy to
to generate so you just have these
parameters are just attraction and
repulsion between different color
particles so so you just Define how much
red particles attracted to read
particles and then you let the
simulation run and you will as you find
in this so maybe maybe if you are
interested I can give you a live demo is
it possible is okay oh
yeah okay so so so so if you go to the
GitHub uh there is actually a link a
JavaScript uh let me let me reshare the
screen
okay so so you can't see the the the the
the screen okay so so if you go to the
GitHub uh hun
4321 particle life uh and then we have a
downloadable version so you can download
it and we have an online version a 2d
online version so let me just open that
2D online version I hope you can still
see it do you see it or should I Y and
I'm I'm also pasting it in the chat so
people can go to it okay so the
interesting thing is so you see I I will
just so here are the parameters so so
I'm trying to change the parameters but
even if you push the random button so
here is a random button so this random
button will just randomly revisit the
attraction
rep Force so even even if you push the R
button you can still see interesting
patterns emerging on the screen so let
me
Zoom yeah so so I'm I'm now just so you
can see I'm just now pushing the random
butter and you see cellular things
like very very interesting
things coming
to so so we will come soon to Mark of
blankets you'll see that Mark of blanket
is very natural it's something when you
have local rules that's what car froston
usually says when you have local rules
there will be always a mark of bran so
because we have local rules but if
Global so the attraction are repuls
rules they have a threshold so you
usually say this particle can attract
this particle but there is a cold it
can't it can't attract very far
particles the same power as very nearby
particles just like in real life just
like the gravity in real life so you can
let these systems evolve they will
produce but what interests me is even if
you push the random buttons the random
uh uh this random rul push it and and
you will have interesting
patterns wow right there just like these
chasing chasing
around got the so now you see a bit a
bit stability now you can see a
stability but this stability will not go
forever because of computational R
sometimes something comes to disturb
system so now they have a mark of
blanket they live happy they they they
have their internal system but at some
point you see this okay now the the
system is
Disturbed so they they they liveed for a
period of time they have nice Mark of
blanket but there something outside
happen don't know that's the uh the
halting problem is could you look at
this at a given time all the rules you
know every single particle State all the
rules could you say what the final end
point will be or what will happen in a
certain number of steps and you might
have a heris but you can't know without
actually going through the
procedure without actually going through
with me simulating the system I mean if
why if I want to predict the future I
have I should have a super computer that
is faster than this I should put the
initial settings and the superc computer
can simulate the system faster than me
but but if I am living inside this
system I don't have this Leisure to to
see the system faster than it so how one
other one other interesting piece there
which you've brought up a few times with
like having a more powerful computer
somehow outside the system so as you
start to look deeper and deeper into
Futures it's almost like the procedure
has runtime n like it's just whatever
complexity class it is it's just one or
X but if you start looking further and
further ahead there are more and more
adjacent possible so that you actually
it's like trying to run up a wall that's
getting exponentially steeper because
the the faster supercomputer even if
it's it's a million times faster but
then if it starts looking several time
steps ahead each of those time steps
have a bigger and bigger adjacent
possible So eventually that one
millionfold increase gets eaten up
pretty
fast yes
yes yes so so that's why I think this
part actually car is this paper that it
has primordial suit but he usually I
think he uses mlab and then so I mean
people nowadays usually use more
sophisticated tools M that have nicer
visualizations and and you actually
couldn't find these interesting pattern
if if you do not have a real system so
so when I was cing this system it's
impossible to find interesting patterns
without having a guy a guy system to
explore easily in real time uh and that
that's what made us
discover so many many interesting
patterns so now there are other systems
that are similar to it actually I think
there is a system called lenia which are
smoother I think it's also very
interesting but the reason why I like
that it very naturally connects to mark
of blankets and and active energy so so
I will actually now go to to what we can
actually elist from these systems and
how can how can we uh do abstractions
and how can we reconnect what we have
learned to our findings that I explained
in the beginning of the video so let me
share reshare my uh uh my screen
again uh so I'm I'm sharing the slides
again okay so so you can see the slides
again yep okay so you saw like like
these parameters I found these
interesting patterns but somebody can
reproduce it if I download the software
the C++ one not the online one because
the c+1 one is more powerful you can
simulate more particles without u i mean
the computer can handle it so so you can
find amazing amazing patterns just and
this just four particles four colored
particles I mean you can go five colored
particles six colored
particles okay so why so my point is how
how how course can help us uh in in this
case so let's say uh I mean this Buck
shape to be quite honest I actually
produce this bug shape
from from so so so this is also not the
pro part the pro part is just for the
illustration but this bug which you can
see this is from the particle life
simulations this is believe it or not
this is just from these rules and I
accidentally happened to me so green
attracts to Green with this power red
green attracts red or repuls red I I
forget whether the negative is
attraction or the positive but but these
simple rules of attractions it can
produce you this flying shape a bug like
flying shape so this is some screenshots
uh how how it how it flies around so my
point is that let's say this frog is
inside this system and it's a predator
it wants to predict because without
prediction you can't catch this F you
can't catch this part but the frog is
inside the system according to
computational pre it can't simulate the
system faster than itself so it can't
know the only way it can do is does some
some way of abstraction and the easiest
abstraction as we say is course graining
so if if you do course graining so here
I did course graining this is not a
simulation it's just illustration to be
quite but I think it's tvial to
understand so so now the number of
particles becomes 70 particles so if the
if the brain of the Frog it just samples
the the it just do sample all the 600
particles it just samples based on
locality I mean local things sample them
and then
uh in the future I mean repetitively
local things will be aggregated together
you will have a a CO grained image and
this course grain image is very very
easier to simulate for the Frog now it
deals with 7 particles instead of 600
particles and that's why maybe even if
the frog is inside the system it can
actually predict the simulation of
course it won't be exactly the same
simulation because we are simulating a
course grained
world but it it should it it will be
close enough it will be close enough for
the FR to survive so so if you do the
real simulation the the bug may be go
this way and then go this way but if you
do the course train simulation inside
the brain of the Frog the it may pred a
different path but if the path is close
enough for the Frog to survive then
that's it so this is what we come here
into a very interesting conclusion
living things like a frog will value
accuracy and will value efficiency it
values both accuracy and efficiency so
you see we we we are closely intuitively
coming to the pre energy principle which
tells which is tells you you have to
minimize surprise and complexity that's
what the equation of free energy so so
it's the same you you you can say so let
let me go actually I I explained that in
the video that course graining is a very
underrated concept it's it's used in
physics in chemistry do you know there
is in physics there are so many theories
under the name of effective theories
they use course graining to explain so
many things and usually do you do not
see physicists telling people oh we
predicted but we used course graining i
i s that this is like hiding a different
fact because we usually talk about
uncertainity principle and things like
that okay but you use you use course
graining course graining is part of
uncertainty so so in this simulation now
it's true that we can predict the bug
but now we are less certain about the
individual particles because we did Co
graining but but that was okay for us
because the aim of the frog is to
predict the whole system not the
individual particles so I'm actually
surprised why physic usually don't
explicit say hey we use for
graining so they they used everywh to be
quite honest so many theories of physics
depend on they they just use all they
even only when you go to the details
you'll find them they have course grain
the system before doing the simulations
whether it's a flute system a particle
system
anything well well I think everything is
course grain don't think we can measure
anything precisely so course graining is
there whether we like it or
not okay Mark of blankets I think Mark
of blankets is well explained car FR
have many many videos about a mark of
blankets so Mark of blankets is a
different way uh of abstracting
information so the nodes that are
surrounding let's say we want to predict
X so if we want to predict X exactly we
have to know the we have to know the
position and the velocity of the
particles in the system but according to
mark of blanket you don't have to if you
know the state of the mark of blanket
you only need to simulate the state but
the problem is how do we know the state
of the mark of blanket we know we need
to know the state of their Mark of
blanket but how do you know the state of
so so that will defeat the purpose it
means that we have to simulate the
entire system but as I said luckily
these Mark of blankets are sparsely
connected I mean you you sometimes see
uh the world the reason to be quite
honest I'm still not sure why why our
world is sparsely connected the only
reason that comes to my mind is because
we have different Force ranges we have
nuclear force which is very very short
range we have uh electromagnetic force
which is wider range we have gravity
force and then because there is a speed
limit of light if you combine the speed
of limit of light and the the range of
forces you can have various ranges of
forces just like just like in our
simulation so just like in our
simulation so we can also say that the
particle simulation is also sparely
connected because we have simulated
different ranges of forses that's why
close by particles so if they they will
arrange sooner to to produce lumps so
that's why I think a mark of blankets
are possible stable Mark of blankets are
POS because of of sparely connected
system why sply connected system because
of different range forces that's my my
explanation for that and this makes
prediction easier now the reason why I
think this makes prediction
easier uh so I will give you this
example last example of partic
simulation because to be quite honest
the reason why I like partical
simulation is it gives you intuition
about a lot of things so one of the
intuitions I usually pull up stepen
wolfram's video he usually say oh I
understand entropy now I think entropy
is the feature of observers because we
observers are computationally limited
that's why entropy is there I was
usually think what the what the hell
he's talking
about it's a bit so I finally have AA
moment when I was trying to understand
how entropy works when watching these
particle systems so so let's say this
was the initial uh set of the before we
start the simulation this is all the
particles if if somebody sees this
system it says this system have half
High entropy it's intuitive I mean even
if we don't specifically Define what's
entropy here it's it this system is all
spared around different colors
everywhere so if I tell you can you
predict what will happen to this
particle here at the middle which in
circle by the where does this particle
go h i mean you don't know I'm sure you
don't know the reason you don't know
even you have the rule is just your
brain cannot cannot simulate all the
particles inside your brain are the
forces you can't you can't figure out
what's the direction of this particle
will it go this way this way but if your
brain is unlimited power I mean if you
can compute all these particles right
away there is no uncertainty you can
tell me I know this particle will go
this direction but the reason you can't
tell me because you can't compute all
these particles now as the system
evolves like you you let the system
now we have different entities with
different Mark of blankets they are
stable so you have chunkers so now your
brain can meaningfully course grain so
so you can easily course grain you can
say oh we have four systems and these
four systems they appr everything so now
if I tell you can you tell me where this
dot goes according to the attraction
rules I think now you can say you can
say oh this this dot is very close I
think it will go down
so the entropy in your brain is
increased so the the entropy I mean the
way that the uncertainity is decreased
sorry because now you can predict where
this dot will go and the reason you go
because now your brain can compute what
happens because because your brain
chunked course grain all these particles
together as one
entity that's because of the mark of
blanket or because of these stable
blankets which which encapsulate the
entities you you treat them as one
entity and the system is now become more
predictable so now you can tell these
particles will go downward and uh and
you can say this will go from high
energy to low energy so so basically you
can use these particle systems I
actually didn't do that it's in my plan
to do actual simulations not just
intuition about these systems so this is
Gibs free energy in which car pron
actually deres from the concept of page
in the living beings it just relates
entropy with
enthalpy so so we know the entropy of
systems increase but local entropy
because of these local forces local
entropy decreases but the entropy
overall entropy decreases because
particles will go down and then uh the
energy as a light will will go into the
universe basically these simulations are
so simple to capture all the detail
but all the details the global entropy
either stays same or increase but the
local entropy decrease and that's what
self-organizing systems like us living
beings will try to do they will go to
that so so what ceston does is
generalize this concept to living beings
and uh to be quite honest I don't know
the details that he do that but he
usually use these
sequence langine equations with pullback
attractors fuer plank equation M then he
comes to the m of blank once it reaches
the back of blanket it can connect to
the Living World basian world and then
and then we have so these partical world
can be connected with living world
that's what car usually does and the
interesting thing it's the same
objective so that the high leval
equation in which the
carg pap uses it just you have a living
systems want to reduce surprise and want
to reduce
complexity and if you remember we told
you because of computational
irreducibility we want to be efficient
and we want to increase the accuracy so
we reach the same intuition without
driving it just because we have
computation we have to be efficient
there is no way around that so this part
and that's what makes because long time
ago I didn't understand what's exactly
the difference between fre energy
principle and the predictive coding so
the main difference is that the Fergy
principle also added efficiency it says
that we try to predict but we also try
to be as efficient as possible as as
simple principle way or the least action
uh way so it may it tries to reduce the
complexity and I think that the the
reason why we want to reduce the
complexity is because we have comped
principle so now we come to active
inference because according to active
inference there is a trick we can do we
can not only predict the system by
learning about we can actually be
participate in the system so so you
either learn from the word uh which I
call to bottom up system or Teach the
World Teach the World it means you you
are trying to change the world so it's
just like if you go back to this to this
particle it's just like you see so this
particle either it attracts the entire
system to itself or either the particle
goes to the bigger system so we
individuals also do that either we are
trying to change the community or either
we adapt to the community and we usually
have to do the the later the majority of
us will be just slaves like we will just
say we can't change the world usually
but I think the analogy is very easy to
to
see
uh so so there are a lot of questions uh
so I I usually usually this question
comes up if we try to predict the
systems why we just don't go to the dark
room uh I see I I I also see the answer
to this from the computational
reducibility principle because
computation doesn't let you there will
be always emergent factors so locally
you can do that as an individual but
collectively we can we can do that
because the system will always change uh
this is analogous another example which
I like I don't see it's used why we
don't use fascism because fascism
actually makes the system predictable
everything behaves According to some
order uh I mean we can use a less uh
inflammatory word than fascism actually
actually people do that people to try I
mean you can see religion
as a way to make everything predictable
so if if you follow a community a strict
Community they will tell you you should
behave that you should do that the holy
day will come out so everything will
become predictable and that's why these
systems sometimes are appealing for
people because it it encapsulates the
idea but the problem with that again
computational res doesn't let you to
live that forever there will be you will
be trapped at a a local Maxima and that
and you you can do that you can live in
this predictable system for years for
thousand thousands of years but the
outside world will always change will
always change and at some point these
changes will either affect you
collectively or individually that's why
we have to change so
so that's why we have curiosity we want
to learn I mean we can never so so
according to the simulations that have
been done in free energy principle even
these particle systems they are actually
modeling the outside the reason why they
did that so if you if you try to uh
follow the activity of these particles
they you will see they are correlating
with the outside if a change happens in
outside you'll see a change happens in
the inside so as if the inside of these
entities they are trying to model and
the reason why they are trying to do if
if you see that the mark of blanket just
actually just looks like a neural
network so it has sensory nodes it have
inter internal nodes it has active nodes
so it's just like a neural network it's
just like how how how it's train so
either use evolutionary technique to
train it the the some blankets survive
some will not survive so we are using
evolutionary technique to train it or
you can use back propagation or you can
use the technique that happens inside
our brain it's hian learning although
there are lot of announc how how
learning happens in our brain but but
the thing is
same so so nested levels of Mark of
blanket you can see it as a nested level
of of neural net it's same it's same
level of
abstraction uh okay so so that's what
makes us that's what I'm saying we can
beat the computational irreducibility
because so all the
brains are local they they can't compute
the entire system but collectively the
the lower brains they abstract the
information they don't send the entire
information to the upper the higher
level brain they abstract it away and
they so the the leval brain even though
it's computationally very limited it has
the same it can actually simulate the
system because it's abstracted it's
course
grain uh so I it's usually a balance
between top down bottom up so basically
what happens is that the inner levels
will be more predictable but the outer
ede will always be less predictable or
the higher levels will always be and we
are I'm usually saying Consciousness
lives at the higher level age of
uncertainty so we have subconscious
everything is predictable like for
example if a fire here my hand will go
away the the the GL ganglions in our
spinal cord will decide even before goes
to our brain the decision so predictable
things are happens in your subconscious
the unpredictable things happens in our
conscious
uh okay I think uh I think I have tried
to explain all the important things that
I want to do but but just before
finishing the uh I want to just
reconnect this concept uh back so so far
we are talking about how do we do
abstractions we generally the best
abstraction as I said we have neural
networks and how neural network work
using back propagation and how back
propagation work we really don't
understand even people who who who
produce Char they say we can qu
the the system for you but we don't know
how back propagation will decide how
abstractions are fored so I I mean few
years ago I came across a algorithm
which is which actually uh drives multi
linear regression I I thought this is
beautiful because it it matches with our
predictions with with our simulations
very very well the the simulations that
I did in the beginning so uh I don't
know have you heard about lattice
filters lattice
filters yeah go go for it though
continue yeah so latus filters are
actually they used all the way in kman
filters and Signal processing filters
and I just don't know why they are less
famous in the machine Learning Community
they are more if if you go to the signal
processing Community you will see a lot
of talk about Lattis filters and K
filter and things like that for me lce
filters are actually very very similar
to how the brain is depicted how because
the predictive coding system will tell
you we have predictions and we have
prediction errors and they they match
very very uh neatly together and these
lce filters are very very easily derived
so if you have two groups for example uh
let's say we want to see which group are
more liable to have a blood high blood
sugar we have obase group and uh less
obesity and usually in scientific tests
we have more variations and these
variations will affect our results so
the best experimental design is to
remove these variations uh that that's
what we say control design but sometimes
you can't do that you can there will be
always variations so many multifactorial
that you even not aware of it so what
you can do that you can do that post H
uh so so let's say we here X we we want
to predict X these X's using X3 and what
what's not predicted is we call them
prediction error so the prediction error
will go to to the upper levels and then
we use the residual errors to predict
the the other remaining errors so you do
that until you end up with the last uh
prediction error which represents this
feature in this case obesity this is
where you you can actually find the
relation with obesity and uh why the
factor that you want to test and if you
do that squential for a squential data
you actually end up deriving the Lattis
filter again which which I talked about
here so you can you you will drive latus
filter and this latus filter is actually
very very similar to how a prediction
error works and this this way it's
similar to what our findings in in our
paper when we say the expected stimuli
will be suppressed so these L filter
will also tell you the same thing it
will tell
you in multivari linear regation we are
trying to predict the stimulate the
prediction error which is not predicted
it will go to the upper level and then
the the outer context will try to
predict that
and you will go increase the context to
predict the remaining errors so I
thought this is really an interesting
connection but these ltis are not used
in machine learning the reason is
because mostly they are linear systems
there are ways that you can make it
nonlinear but they are because they
learn very fast they are very very
sensitive to noise so if you have a big
small noise they will just learn the
noise too and that's why that's why I
think people in machine Learning System
they actually go to uh use optimization
methods using back propagation because
in back propagation you have a learning
rate which you can reduce it that means
even if a noise comes it will not affect
the entire system so that's why my only
explanation why people don't use this
method but I like this method because it
connects our brain the predictive coding
error and it it is very similar to the
uh findings that we have in our paper
and and I think it connects nicely
somehow to to the free energy
principle
so uh thank you a lot for for for uh
listening and I'm here if you have any
questions
awesome okay well thanks for the awesome
and and wide ranging presentation while
I crop and get everything back if anyone
wants to write a question in the chat go
for it and just to kind of begin the
discussion I mean could you share a
little bit H how how did you get to
studying the
suppression uh repetition suppression in
your PhD then what what Journey has
brought you to making the self
organizing particles and all the cool
YouTube
videos oh thank you uh well repetition
suppression
uh it's my PhD supervisor is actually a
very big name in repetition separation
so he he have a lot of reviewed uh
review papers on repetition
suppression and I found this is
interesting my beginning PhD I was
interested in episodic memory because
that was my my Master's Degree
uh was about episodic memory uh but but
later on I thought there is a very nice
connection between repetition
suppression and the predictive coding
literature uh by then I wasn't aware too
much with free energy principle but more
aware with
prediction predictive coding literature
so I thought because there is this
connection and and and and it was always
surprising to me uh that the phenomena
of repetition suppression it just means
that when something becomes very
expected when when you when you finally
predict something your brain will go
idle so usually I thought in the
beginning it's counterintuitive because
usually you think oh if something
becomes very predictable you should your
brain should be more active uh but but
that's interestingly not true your brain
is uh is usually what what I think is is
more active at the age of uncertainty
when when you because because let be
honest if you if you see noise it's
completely unpredictable but at some
point your brain will go idle
uninterested so we uh our paper was not
about that but I'm sure if there are
papers uh it's a you care a you shaped
curve so if something is very
predictable your brain will be less
interested less activity and if
something is completely unpredictable
again we we are not interested in it so
I think
the for some reason I think it may be
connected to Consciousness I'm not sure
about my my studies was not about
Consciousness but I think repetition
suppression is probably the the closest
phenomena that we can objectively
examine and it some ways connects
because because
subjectively uh when something BEC
predictable you also feel
it's boring and you feel sleepy so so so
the objective findings that we see the
activity decreases also correlates with
the subjective findings that we actually
feel and because these are to Connected
I think it's probably the closest uh
objective phenomena that we can test and
somehow we can correlate to
Consciousness yeah I mean the example of
the just a random pattern
that could be intelligently core grained
and you go okay frame after frame the
core graining of this whole picture is
just gray so then the cor graining is
unsurprising so then even if the pixel
level details are still surprising
you've reduced or bounded surprise at
the slower or the deeper layer so again
that becomes not
interesting oh wow that's actually a
video so so I I actually didn't thought
about it like that but the course
graining idea if you combine it it will
it will just reconnect back to the more
that that's very nice actually I really
liked how you connected the core scening
with the the Markov blanket a lot of
work has connected neural networks and
the loss function that's used in
training the neural network with the
variational free energy and then in the
neuroimaging setting core screening like
you brought up it's a really simple
heris CU it's just spatial proximity you
don't need to Cluster things by their
functional similarity you just use the
anatomy and then it's interesting to
think about the Markov blankets as coar
graining in a causal space like if you
had um 10 10 different uh sub
procedures but then you say well one
procedure one two and three are like one
unit and then that becomes like its own
thing but procedure one might be
anatomically close to seven but then 1
two and three are causal and so then
it's like building these parallel maps
from your PhD it was more grounded in
the spatial in the temporal and then the
Markov blanket abstracts that into a
causal but then abstracting away from
space and time is where we get patterns
and that is how abstraction helps us
predict the future
exactly oh that this is interesting I
think I think I think course braining is
just like a door for understanding so
many things and I usually I I sometimes
interested in physics to be quite even
in my high school I was interested in
physics I don't have a formal education
in physics but I am very very interested
and I am very very interested in the
phenomenas of uncertainty principle and
and Bill phenoma and and I usually I'm
afraid to ask physic because they
usually get angly is there a relation
between course graining and uncertainty
they usually tell you no and uncertainty
in physics is
fundamental they I I don't know whether
they maybe there are maybe physicist
outside outli physicist like Steven wam
or uh some other physicist they they
have more deterministic uh uh view of
what certainity means or what Randomness
means at the lower level but to my
experience usually when I go discussing
Reddit groups and they will get angry
they will say no you don't understand
anything about the
underlying atoms they will just go
random it's just a a true random
generator well I I I don't know who will
get mad about what but in a way the
movement from Quantum scale physics to
classical physics is like core scening
it's like saying well if you go to one
atom it might be difficult to know what
Vector it's going to move in next even
if you knew the temperature maybe that's
near the limits of of um a true
ontological uncertainty but then if you
have a ball moving through space you can
get a really good prediction on a slower
larger thing and then that's classical
mechanics where you don't have the same
uncertainty you can just assume this
basically infinite Precision but then
Quantum is where you can't assume
infinite precision and people whether
that's ontologically how it is at a
certain scale or whether that's an
artifact of our interfacing with small
things but regardless things that are
about as big as we are it's kind of like
these are like pebbles that are about as
big as we can pick up those are the
things that we can think about that's
what makes sense to us and then those
are the classics and then things that
are um more challenging to abstract or
predict they're nonsensical or they're
they're outside of our our scope of
understanding
yes um but but from earlier H how did
you get from the repetition suppression
to
to working on what you're doing now and
and making cool
videos uh actually uh
particle making
videos as I told you before I actually
learn more when I make a video about a
topic so I call that Active Learning uh
there are so many topics that in my life
I want to try learning it's just like
because I see many intelligent people
they say oh this this topic is very
important this topic is so right now in
in current situation I trying to learn
Mona and I I I look at many videos I
don't know what the hell they are
talking about but because so many
intelligent people they say oh monat is
a very interesting way of abstraction in
programming just like I have to learn
that and at some point I think when I
fail understanding it I say oh if I have
if I if I try to make a video on it I
will finally understand it so usually
making videos on something it actually
pushes you to understand it I don't know
why this is true but I find it very
interesting because our brain course
gains a lot of information and self
attention it always tells you this is
not interesting this is not interesting
it has a lot of a big selectivity so
this part of selectivity tells you which
direction you go so when you make a
video on something it will actually now
say okay now I I know this is important
so it gives
you it g it makes your attention on on
the topic without that it will always
something tells you to procrastinate and
not not pay attention to it so the
reason why I make videos is just
interest to be quite honest I make
videos when there is some idea and I
like to represent I I like to learn
about it and I like to represent that in
a video uh so one of the these ideas
which I like local Maxima idea I I find
it it fascinating and actually it links
back to computational irreducibly in
some way because local Maxima tells you
that because we are limited because our
brain limited we we every now and then
we will be trapped on a local Maxima and
that will be very difficult when we tra
on a local that's it we we have to
become conservatives there is no way
around either you risk something some
people risk their lives go outside
otherwise local Maxima the direction
will be
lost when when you when you are trapped
on so that idea was very interesting and
particle simulations I was trying to
explain to some friends how because
usually when you discuss Evolution
Theory they will tell you how P cells
arise and I thought I I most thought the
fair cells are actually easy to explain
I mean people usually think that the
fair cells are the complicated cells
like now we see no the fair cells are
probably just a membrane and a nucleus
and I thought that this is very easy to
simulate with some particles attracting
each other and I was looking at YouTube
videos to see and then I came across
this particle life system uh I don't
remember the name of the guy but he was
explaining uh these uh cellular shapes
with attraction and repetion forces and
I thought wow this is very interesting
actually I tried to implement that by
myself and I improvised that and I was
surprised I was trying to do that and
then a buck on my screen appeared a
flying buck so that was very very
surprising I was shocked I mean how how
can I I I'm just randomly examining some
simple rules and I see something like a
flag and then I actually uh made made a
video and that video actually have a lot
of views and the code have a lot of
participants they they made the code way
more sophisticated so now it has a lot
of gooey parts and thanks to the
participants uh and I think I think it's
the the most
uh
uh yeah I mean many many people actually
become more popular the particle life uh
after that video and the reason why I
think is because the code was the
simplest possible code I thought I
thought because it is educational I have
to make it the simple as possible I I
actually reduced all the parts that I
thought uh it may not be interesting and
because the code is very simple and the
patterns is very complex I thought that
that's what attracted and I hoping more
people actually come to the partic life
because I know game of life is very
interesting it's touring complete it's
very but particle life is less known
about but they are more biologically
looking yeah lot lot lot of insights
there about the formation of well first
the joy and the fun of Open Source and
of people's participation in science
around the world and then in the first
cells forming there's like hydrophobic
and hydrophilic and then also ex that's
that my concept
about how so how the material gets there
is is you know these are all inquiry to
to explore and then also just just about
the videos so one thing about video is
it's it's an audio and a visual
component now some videos you can watch
with no audio and and vice versa um but
when audio and visual are happening
together it's kind of like two touches
from across the Marco blanket like if
someone's doing hand gestures while
they're talking then they're both being
emitted from the same cognitive state
whereas if if it scrambled what hand
gestures were happening with the audio
it would remove that meaning but
synchronously they're experienced
together so then they're seen as
meaningful so then like I was paying
attention to the presentation and it was
like slide after slide I would be
initially surprised and then through
through the suppression of surprise I I
keep seeing in in these two images here
it's like sometimes you connect with a
layer above or below which is top down
from the Top's perspective or bottom up
from the Bottom's perspec or you go
sideways and so that could be in a grid
World lateral spatial that could be
through time like on a timeline it's
like those are the local moves that can
be made you can move up or down a layer
of abstraction and
generalization and then you can move
around in space and time and cause it's
like those are our that's like the
pushup and the pullup of the local
interactions these are the moves the
dance moves and then the question is
just like what what does the party look
like and that's the particle simulation
what really look what what starts to
happen when all of these moves what if
some of the particles can do
abstraction
yes yeah um by can I show you a demo
another oh yeah go for it okay so uh so
so this laus filter I I I do have a a
video another video on it but I have
also a demo so I I I can show you a
python code uh so let me open up my so
do do you code in Python I I saw you you
code in Python what what IDE do you use
um I I use uh cursor for the AI
augmentation or just vs
code oh Visual Studio code I use a
what's called spider oh yeah for for
Scientific Python yes it's very similar
to mlab because in my PhD I I LIF M up I
I I hate it as a language but it's very
nice IDE it has a very nice ID hate it
as a language love it as a
friend
exactly so when I trans transition to
python code I saw spider as a home
because it looked like P
uh it looked like
uh the M lab the yeah also like R
Studio oh yeah
yeah okay so so you see them ID now huh
yep go for
it
great so let
me for
okay so I'm pasting a
previous
okay let me paste a put from
okay so can you see
uh can you see the code okay yep
yep okay
so so this is I I I like this algorithm
uh I people usually call it ltis filters
uh as I said I drive this algorithm just
from the prediction coding uh multi
linear regression system and I have a
video about that uh it it's titled
regression and brain so it's very very
simple code but it somewhat explains
repetition
suppression
so if you if you run the code okay so
now this this will this is activity this
is the error and this is by the way do
you do you see the plots or you just see
the spider IDE no plots just the
IDE okay so I have to share the screen
the screen is better so
let me share the
screen I think you should see all right
looks good okay great so I run the
code uh and this is the pattern so so
let's let's simulate a sinodal pattern
in the beginning so so let's say we are
just simulating signus
okay so this is the truth the green and
the and the Orange is the prediction you
see in the beginning it doesn't predict
the the the Orange Line doesn't overlay
the blue light the sinusal activity so
the sinusal activity is our data the
truth and and the prediction is that is
the algorithm which I showed you it's
just it's just few lines of quote here
so I I will just explain it right now
but but the interesting connection I'll
try to make to repetition
suppression
so it see you see after few iteration it
can perfectly predict the the sosal
activity uh and and you see the error
plot actually reducing in the beginning
it's high but then it's reducing uh to
zero and and this actually tells you how
much activity do we have in in different
layers so you can see in the beginning
in the lower layers we have higher
activity let let me zoom in so we have
higher activity in the lower layers and
then as we go to the upper layers we
have less activity that's why because
because the system can predict what
Captain this now I will introduce a
surprise to this system let me uh in
this code now I'm am for every
for every two steps I am just changing y
to one it means just sinusoidal wave but
I'm introducing one to it so it's just
like now we have a
surprise okay now you see it's it's more
difficult so in the beginning it can't
predict the entire system but then later
on it learns it learns to predict the
squence so you see it's just same sign
but I have introduced number one uh I
have introduced something
surprising uh but then later on it
predicts and then the error goes down
and then again we have the
activities uh but now the activities can
go to higher layers before it it's
suppressed to zero okay now I I will
just introduce one surprising
event so just minus one at at 17 so at
17 I will just introduce a a surprise to
the sequence
and see what the algorithm how the
algorithm behave okay so you
see okay so you see it predicts the
system but here when I introduced a
surprise it it can't predict it it can't
fit the
data
and and if you see the activity you see
when the at the level at this level when
I introduce the L Sur prise you can see
the prediction error goes all the way
the upper layers so just like repetition
supression when you see something
surprising the activity increases so
just like that in the beginning so this
algorithm is actually a very nice view
to tell us how our brain may be working
and and here we we even see that that
almost
diagonal
propagation up and to the right as it
sort of normalizes and calms down at
higher exactly exactly so so maybe maybe
that good thing and a bad thing because
the algorithm learns very learns this
surprise that's why even in the upcoming
uh steps it it needed some time to come
back so maybe maybe maybe we can put a
filter there we can say oh if the
prediction error is very high don't
learn the pattern so maybe we can put a
thresold and maybe that will actually
tells me that's why we have belief
system in ours that's why our brain is
actually fixed on some idea sometimes if
something very surprising and it doesn't
conform with your previous
beliefs because the learning algorithm
inside our brain is very
fast if we can learn everything that
even if doesn't conform to our previous
beliefs it means it can mess up
sometimes they it's similar to
catastrophic forgetting it's just like
the activity the new activity May
superimpose to the previous activities
in your brain and can mess up everything
and that's why maybe some people are
actually hard to change their minds
even when they say new data when they
see new things uh people usually if if
if it doesn't conform with their beliefs
they will just deny it because sometimes
you need to fix that you need for this
surprise to become a pattern so that
your brain surrenders says Okay I want
to learn that that's what I think I mean
I think this algorithm can tell us more
about our brain that we
even uh so so it's very very easy it's
just it's just like the prediction yourr
system so so you have a sequence of data
Ys and then you just have just just
focus on these two lines because
everything happens here so you have so
you just have a forward prediction and
backward prediction basically W this is
the weight multiplied by the activity
current activity it will try to predict
the future activity F and the
substraction the difference between
these two is the prediction error so if
that that prediction error will go to
the upper level so we have a a nice
illustration on that so so this
is the code just illustrates this so y5
here this tries predict Y y4 and then
the prediction error goes up and then y
tries to predict wi5 the prediction the
the forward prediction and the backward
prediction so the prediction error we
have two prediction error the forward
prediction error and the backward
prediction error so each level tries to
predict the previous prediction error
and each prediction error will go up
hierarchy and hopefully at the higher
hierarchy you will have less prediction
error it means like your brain can
predict
everything I I'll just add a note on
prediction error the prediction error is
denominated in the units of the
measurement like if you expect the room
to be 30° and it's 31 then the error is
one and then the move in active
inference is to translate that error
signal into information units bits
surprise and then surprise if you can
compute it exactly for a simple system
go for it but then in cases where it's
intractable or you want to do an
optimization on bounding surprise that's
variational free energy and that's been
used for decades variational Auto
encoder all these other kinds of
variational methods and
physics so those are all kind of aligned
like if you B if the error were zero the
surprise would be minimal the free
energy would be minimal if there's a
large error the surprise is higher the
variational free energy is higher so
like they're slightly different
formulations but they're all
monotonically related they related I
think they are
using other optimization algorithms to
learn this so they maybe better
optimization that's what I say that you
have to learn gradual the the problem
with this system it learns try to
exactly learn and that's why when you
show something
surprises prediction explodes well that
that kind of even comes back to the
earlier numbers that you showed with the
decimal points it's like um are you
trying to predict to one significant
figure that's core scening to just one
digit but then if you give a computer
program a float Precision number it
might have a ton of decimal points and
then it will think that those are just
as important to compute as the earlier
decimal points and then it gets
catastrophic because it's doing really
well on like the the 50th decimal point
but it lost the plot on the main thrust
oh I
sometimes Precision error uh by the way
floating floating Point numbers are also
a form of course graining because we
can't actually simulate real numbers
real numbers have infinite Precision so
so the moment we say we used floating
point it means we have course grain the
real number there is no way without
course graining even in in the computers
even if you see if you use double
Precision it's it's just you have at
some point you just cut the the
number yeah um cool so what are your
next research or or directions that
you're going to be
exploring okay there are two directions
one is I actually want to explore more
free energy what happens in these
particle systems but not just
intuitively because to be quite honest
the things that I showed you some some
stuff that I thought it is Trivial we
don't need to even simulate it uh
but I I I have to simulate that because
sometimes simulations gave you surprised
just like the first example which I
showed you I mean you think this happens
because of this but sometimes this is
not true uh the next thing I am actually
working on a different algorithm I call
it fun predictive hean unified
neurons uh I am so far I'm not
successful with this algorithm we can
see this algorithm is a variant of this
algorithm which I just showed you uh but
but I'm trying to make this algorithm
more local I mean learn locally uh the
problem is because you so so what's the
problem with the current neural network
approach the neural network works very
good we we saw magic with GPT but the
problem is these systems they learn very
F very slow uh training they have sample
in efficient they you have to give them
so many samples so that they can learn
the reason why because they you have to
tweak the learning rate to to lower
levels because if you tweak the learning
late higher if the system learns fast it
will have a catastrophic forgetting that
the moment it it sees something new
novel it's because it has high learning
rate it tries to incorporate that new
thing into all the systems all the
neuron Network nodes and because these
systems are distributed it means it
tries to F between every node every
weight and that could be catastrophic
especially if this outlier is just a
noise it's just an noise you need
to ignore it but if you have a high
learning rate algorithm doesn't can't
learn it that's why you have to make the
learning rate small but if you make the
learning rate small it means you have
have to iteratively learn so many
samples and variations and that's why
only big companies nowadays can train
neural networks because it it needs so
many iterations and even these big
companies they can't make a realtime
system so even if they make a robot that
robot can't learn on real time it's just
like the company can tell you oh this
this robot can only learn do things that
we have trained in in
2020 you have we have to take it back
and update and retrain again on on the
data from 20 23 or something like that
so it's not real time Learning System so
even Char now is not a real time
Learning System it if if open a I need
to retrained again it needed it updated
it needed to retrain everything again so
basically it means these algorithms are
not real time but this algorithm is real
time the one I showed you means once you
see the data in in just few samples it
learns it but again the problem with
this algorithm is this catastrophic
disturbance I mean this unstability once
it sees something surprising because it
tries to learn it it it just messes up
and that's uh that's uh what I try to
figure out something that lears fast but
it doesn't disturb the entire
system so I'm I'm actually trying to do
that uh but so far not very successful
but but every now then I I have ideas to
implement and then try again and again
uh I think now I I I mean few months ago
I have a new but I still don't have time
to implement it so maybe maybe you can
hear more about me in in the future
about the predictive hean unified
neurons which I shortly call it fun
which which is not fun to
it doesn't work it's not fun
yet planning for fun is still
fun um okay do you have any last
comments uh no thank you very much for
actually inviting me inviting me to to
this uh and I hope you continue I
actually find active inference uh uh
Channel very interesting and I find the
topic is very interesting actually the
entire topic that you specialized
yourself to just this one topic and it's
a very very interest I I thought is a
very good candidate for The Theory of
Everything I mean people usually think
that the theory of everything should
come from physics but I think it will
come from Neuroscience that's
why I mean it it doesn't make sense to
have a theory of everything without
Consciousness that's why it has to come
from Neuroscience I mean physics can
help in Neuroscience but The Theory of
Everything
it comes from Neuroscience there is no
way around that's my or it comes from a
new combinatoric Fusion I mean one of
the key Moves In free energy principle
is to talk about the cognitive particle
so then if it's a basian mechanics if
it's a statistical physics for cognitive
particles then it's not surprising that
it has a lot to do with particle
physics yes yeah yeah maybe maybe com
that that's the best thing to to
actually do com actually I mean I have
maybe one extra uh animation slide I I I
can show you before sounds good yes
about this combinatory things I usually
show that to to friends and and they
usually like it and I explained that in
in in my videos in some of my
videos so I mean if you if you if you
see this graph as the entire human
knowledge and then this child it it
likes to learn it's just born and it
doesn't know anything so the problem is
our age is very limited so by the time
the the child the Curious child that
tries to collect information it will get
old and it will at some point it will
die before learning about everything and
that that's the
reality okay now what what I think
actually better is specialization it
means that child shouldn't try to learn
everything in the beginning it tries to
learn all the things that are
surrounding and then should
specialize if you specialize at some
point you will reach the age of
knowledge and once you reach the age of
knowledge this is where you can find a
new information the the
extrapolation That's What I Call
extrapolation okay but the problem with
space ization is we will be trapped at a
local Maxima it means so it means if
this guy is a doctor uh it tries to
treat cancer it specializes in cancer
but maybe the true treatment of cancer
comes from an engineer engineering Treck
someone can find a new radiation that
doesn't affect normal cells only affect
uh cancer cells so I mean if you trap
yourself just reading medicine you can
never find this
solution uh so so this solution how how
it comes so let's say uh so so that's my
point you can never make distant
connections long-term connections
because you specialize you you trapped
yourself now if if other people who are
also specialized in different
topics and if they collaborate with each
other that's why I'm coming back to your
so if physics and collaborate with
chemistry with chemists and they
collaborate with
neuroscientists and then this
collaboration we can overcome the local
Maxima
TRS totally agree and there there they
they are working on the
interdisciplinary team sending each
other papers sending each other jokes
and memes that reflect their worldviews
to give a kind of qualitative sense of
their
understanding and also I I think in the
core screening I think about nestmate
ants returning with food and so they're
not saying what temperature or anything
it's just interacting with Nest me yes
there was food someone else came that
way with food and so that's like a
binary coar graining that tells you
something about that direction and so
it's like every node is a local sense
maker receiving and sending and that's
active
inference yes yes that's a nice way to
complet okay unar thank you good luck
with your with your work and with your
education so it's been awesome thank you
very much Danielle see you soon thanks a
lot bye see you
bye for